<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon a late book, entituled, The case of allegiance consider'd wherein is shewn, that the Church of England's doctrine of non-resistance and passive obedience, is not inconsistent with taking the new oaths to Their Present Majesties.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12330273</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12330273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59635</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59635)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 639:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon a late book, entituled, The case of allegiance consider'd wherein is shewn, that the Church of England's doctrine of non-resistance and passive obedience, is not inconsistent with taking the new oaths to Their Present Majesties.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reply to S. Masters's The case of allegiance in our present circumstances consider'd ...</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Masters, Samuel, 1645 or 6-1693. --  Case of allegiance in our present circumstances consider'd.</term>
               <term>Passive resistance --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59635:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59635:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON A Late Book, ENTITULED, <hi>The Caſe of</hi> Allegiance <hi>Conſider'd:</hi> Wherein is ſhewn, that the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Doctrine OF <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> Is not inconſiſtent with Taking <hi>The New Oaths</hi> TO Their Preſent MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licens'd and Enter'd according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59635:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59635:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON A Late Book, ENTITULED, The Caſe of Allegiance conſider'd.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU deſire my Opinion concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and the Treatiſe of <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance;</hi> which I ſent you, hoping that you being of a judgment diſſatisfied in that caſe, it might have ſome influence for your Conviction: But the Anſwer which you returned me with that Book, was, <hi>That you thought the Author to be a partial man, no Miniſter of the Eſtabliſhed Church.</hi> And although the Treatiſe might, as ſome Beauties, have a general approbation, yet there was in it ſomething of an Air which did not pleaſe you; and though you dealt with it, as <hi>Martial</hi> with <hi>Sabadius,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Non Amo te Sabade nec poſſum dicere quare,</l>
                  <l>Hoc tantum poſſum dicere non amo te.</l>
               </q> Yet knowing you to be a good Scholar, and an honeſt man, I reſumed the Book, and gave it a diligent Reſearch;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59635:3"/>and upon ſecond thoughts, am induced to think, that the Author was either of the number of the ancient <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. or of thoſe who of late are known by the name of <hi>Trimmers,</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarian,</hi> much differing in his Principles of Loyalty from thoſe which have been taught and practiſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by the Bleſſing of God it ſtands Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: A City-Miniſter I believe he may be, (as he names himſelf) but whether of the number of thoſe that are by Law Eſtabliſhed, I much doubt:</p>
            <p>However, I do declare, that I am fully ſatisfied as to the deſign of the Author, That we may and ought to pay our Allegiance to King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> whom I pray God long to preſerve and proſper, yet can I not approve of the Premiſes from which he would infer that Concluſion: for notwithſtanding the many Male Adminiſtrations of the late King, I ſuppoſe (with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thoſe that judge otherwiſe) that we ought not, for thoſe Reaſons, to have made actual Reſiſtance (as we did not) by taking Arms againſt him, nor that the late King did thereby forfeit his Right to the Crown, this being, as I yet conceive, contrary to our Oaths and Declarations, and contrary to the Doctrine and Practice of that Church whereof we profeſs our ſelves Members.</p>
            <p>To which I add this Reaſon, becauſe we ſhould hereby juſtifie that unnatural Rebellion which was ſo ſmally car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of bleſſed Memory, againſt whom it was ſuggeſted, That he had been acceſſary to the poiſoning of his Father; that he endeavoured to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce Popery and Arbitrary Government; to bring in <hi>German</hi> Horſe, and other forreign Forces into the Land; and cauſeleſly impoſed Fines and Impriſonment on his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: All which notwithſtanding, I cannot think thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than Rebels, that raiſed War againſt him. And I hope their preſent Majeſties will not be diſpleaſed, if we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59635:3"/>ſtill retain our firſt Principles of Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience, during their Government: Nor once ſuſpect, that they who have maintained and practiſed them under ſuch unhappy Circumſtances, as they were reduced to by the Evil Conduct and Counſels of the late King, will caſt off this which the Author calls <hi>Super-Loyalty;</hi> as if it were contrary to a true Engliſh Temper, and a peaceful Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Church and State. And as for our <hi>Super-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> I think there needs no other Apology than what this Author hath made, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That before the Church was ſecretly practiſed upon by the Arts of her ſubtile Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, (which (by the way) did not prevail either with the chiefeſt for Dignity, or with the moſt for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who perceived the Deſign of our Adverſaries was to divide us, and thereby to deſtroy us) it was eaſily to be diſcovered that her <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Churches Principles of Conformity and Loyalty were far more moderate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible than thoſe which have been ſince that time moſt induſtriouſly and impetuouſly recommended under her venerable Name: So that by this I cannot conceive how the Church ſhould oblige the preſent Government to treat her with leſs kindneſs than ſhe doth expect, as the Author doth ſuggeſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>But here it will be demanded what ſecurity we will give for our Allegiance to the preſent Government, and on what foundation we lay that Allegiance. I anſwer to the firſt, Our Security ſhall be our Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience, which we have always practiſed in far more difficult times and circumſtances, than we can fear to ſee under the preſent Government. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Our Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall be the taking of the New Oaths, which we have ſeen and maturely conſidered, and by the help of God ſhall religiouſly obſerve, as we did our former Oaths, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the late King before his departure did abſolve us from them, and much more by his deſerting of us, and as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59635:4"/>much as in him lay, gave us up to Confuſion: All which notwithſtanding, there are ſtill among us ſome ſober men, ſo nicely ſcrupulous, that they conceive themſelves under the obligation of them; though I doubt not, but the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Members of our Church will be <hi>ex animo,</hi> full Conformiſts to thoſe Oaths.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond demand, on what foundation we lay our Allegiance to the preſent Government, I anſwer, We have an Act of Parliament in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, for our indemnity, as to the Law of the Land; and I think we have a Statute in an higher Court, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> the reaſon whereof is, <hi>for there is no power but of God;</hi> (and) <hi>the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that be,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of which, I ſuppoſe we have no need of the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which our Author doth make, <hi>(viz.)</hi> There is no Authority, if not of God, and the Authorities which are (of God's inſtitution) are ordered under God: for I think our Tranſlation is the beſt, <hi>(viz.) For there is no power but of God, and the powers that are</hi> (i. e.) are in being <hi>de facto, are ordained of God, who giveth them to whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</hi> And it is no difficult task to ſhew that the Power then in being, was but an Uſurpation on the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Army and ſuch Favourites as they ſet up for Emperours, againſt the Right of the Senate; of which, if need were, I could give ſufficient Teſtimonies of very Learned men, nor can I think that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was intended to be underſtood in ſuch a critical ſence, as to ſignifie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely only ſuch Powers as are <hi>de Jure,</hi> lawful.</p>
            <p>But I depend not on either or both of theſe, nor on thoſe overt acts which the late King did wilfully commit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he did abdicate the Government of the Kingdom of <hi>England, quâ talis,</hi> long before he left the Land; for the Government being an Office entruſted for Adminiſtration according to Laws, and the late King's Grandfather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59635:4"/>declared to his Subjects in the <hi>Star Chamber, June</hi> 20. 1616. <hi>that being ſworn to Maintain the Laws of the Land, he ſhould be perjured if he ſhould alter them;</hi> and our ancient Lawyers declaring, that <hi>Non est Rex ubi dominatur voluntas &amp; non lex.</hi> And that of <hi>Fleta, Rex non à regnando ſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo, nam Rex est dum bene regit Tyrannus cùm populum op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primit.</hi> And <hi>Spelman</hi> of the word <hi>Allegiantia,</hi> that it is a word importing <hi>vinculum Arctius inter regem &amp; ſubditos utroſque invicem connectens.</hi> And the reſolution of ſome very judicious Divines, <hi>that if one party that is mutually ingaged, do violate his obligation, the other is not obliged, and that that Oath is not to be kept, the execution whereof is deſtructive of the common ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On theſe grounds many great men may judge, that for theſe and the like cauſes, a Crown may be forſeited; yet I ſuppoſe there are other Foundations layed by thoſe great men in which I do acquieſce: As firſt, that the preſent King being a free Prince, and no Subject of the King of <hi>England,</hi> and having a right Title to the Succeſſion to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as well in his own right as in right of his Queen, whereof he was endeavoured by the ſubtil arts of Jeſuits to be deprived; and the preſent King being alſo conſtituted the Head of the Proteſtant party, who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to utter ruin, by confederacies againſt them, did for theſe cauſes ſucceſsfully vindicate his Title and the legal Succeſſion, and put the Proteſtant Cauſe in a fair way of eſtabliſhment, upon which ſucceſs the late King having deſerted firſt the Government, and then the Land, and fled to an inveterate Enemy of our Religion and Nation, whether through his own or the counſel of the Jeſuits, to whoſe conduct he had committed his Conſcience, and the adminiſtration of the Government, directly contrary to the Laws of the Land, and leaving us under a ſtanding Army, wherein was a conſiderable party of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left unpaid, and ordered to disband, were likely to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59635:5"/>very injurious to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects; I am convinced, that he hath lawfully vindicated the Succeſſion to himſelf and the Royal Family.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, I aſſent to the judgment of my Superiors, that the Crown of <hi>England</hi> being thus made void, was rightfully ſet on the Heads of the preſent King and Queen; and that the preſent Tranſactions are much more juſtifiable than what was done in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, and acknowledged by Parliament; my Reaſons whereof I ſhall give hereafter, and ſhall now give you my Remarks on the <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> wherewith I was generally well pleaſed both with the Matter and Stile, and which, I hope, may have a good effect with many men for their full ſatisfaction, for which I verily believe it was charitably and ingeniouſly intended by the Author, until in the laſt <hi>Page</hi> I read this following paſſage, whereupon I began to make my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, <hi>(viz) That in the next Reign after King</hi> James, (which all know was that glorious Martyr <hi>Charles</hi> Firſt) <hi>when Popiſh and</hi> French <hi>Counſels found admiſſion at our Court, then aroſe together the new Principles of Super-conformity in the Church, and Super-Loyalty in the State, which like a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural ferment, have ever ſince diſturbed the peace of both, and must be again cast out, if ever we recover a true</hi> Engliſh <hi>temper, or peaceful ſettlement,</hi> &amp;c. This, and ſome other paſſages, which I ſhall name, made me ſuſpect, that he was under ſome diſcontent, though <hi>p.</hi> 2. he ſays, <hi>he had no angry reſentment of his ſufferings.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 19. ſpeaking of the Biſhops who petitioned the late King, he calls them, <hi>ſome of his Biſhops.</hi> And of the Clergy he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>There have been for ſome time a Party among us who have appropriated to themſelves the Church of</hi> England, <hi>excluſive of their Brethren, yet we ſhall find enough on our ſide to juſtifie our Doctrines to be conſiſtent with her Principles.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>That the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Loyalty which obtained in the Church at that time,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) <hi>were no other than what he aſſerts.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59635:5"/>He would prove from the Prayer, they are charged with by the Parliament in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign, That God would turn her heart from Idolatry, to the true Faith, or elſe ſhorten her days, and take her quickly out of the way; and more to this purpoſe out of the Journal of <hi>Simon D'Eurs,</hi> of which I doubt not to ſay, that theſe Aſſertions are not agreeable to the Doctrine and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe paſſages did a little amuze me, as reflecting too ſeverely on the beſt of Kings and the moſt diſcreetly Loyal Church in the World. As for the King of Bleſſed Memory, his firſt years were full of peace, till being reduced to ſome neceſſities, not thrô his own fault, but ſuch as by other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy circumſtances he was reduced to, ſome Malecontents took advantage thereof to drive him to greater; the vogue was his being miſled by evil Counſellors, ſuch as the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and <hi>Strafford,</hi> who I have reaſon to believe were as far from <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>French</hi> Counſels, as any Miniſters of State before or ſince. As for that good Prince, I can't with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out indignation hear, that he inclined to Popiſh Counſels, for thô he be termed the head of the <hi>Grotian</hi> Religion, and <hi>Grotius</hi> for an arrant Papiſt, yet it is well known in what Religion he both lived and died, as alſo did thoſe two great Miniſters, the Earl and the Arch-biſhop, of whom Sir <hi>Edw. Dearing</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he had ſmitten the great Champion of the Papiſts under the fifth rib.</hi> And though the King married to a <hi>French</hi> Lady, yet he eſpouſed not her Religion, much leſs the Counſels of that Court to which he was alway a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Yet I remember it was ſaid by a late Writer, <hi>That the Parliament</hi> (whom he was bound to believe) <hi>made it their great argument and advantage against the King, that he favoured the Papiſts;</hi> on which ſuppoſition thouſands came in to fight for their cauſe. And one Article againſt the Arch-biſhop was, <hi>That he endeavoured to introduce Popery;</hi> though Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> proved a deſign of the Papiſts to cut
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59635:6"/>them both off, as their moſt formidable Enemies. And the Relation of Dr. <hi>Du Moulin</hi> ſaith, That at the death of that good King, a known Papiſt was heard to ſay, <hi>That now their greatest Enemy was cut off.</hi> I think no good man will accuſe the Nation of Super-Loyalty in the State, when ſo much real Miſchief was wrought by ſuch groundleſs Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, that cauſed a fatal War againſt ſo Religious a Prince; and by the ſame Arts a preternatural Ferment (as he ſays) has ever ſince diſturbed the Peace of the State.</p>
            <p>As to the other head, the Super-Conformity that troubled the Church, which muſt be caſt out, or (he ſays) there can never be a peaceful Settlement in the Church, I would gladly be informed whether the many Sects which have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded among us, all which conſpired againſt both the Church and State, were not rather the Superfetations of the firſt Nonconformiſts, who raiſed Diviſions in, and Separation from the Church on the like pretences, that the Biſhops were Popiſhly affected: Which Ferment made the Presbyterians and other Sects to impute Popery to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ever ſince the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign; and ſuch a Suſpicion the Author would ſtill cheriſh in the minds of the People. And whether the Author be not ſoured with the ſame Ferment, that calls the Petitioning Biſhops, ſome of his (i. e. <hi>James</hi> the Second's) Biſhops, I much doubt. Nor can I tell how he ſhould be of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet record his Sufferings, unleſs for ſome Nonconformity he was one of the Excluded Brethren; which I gueſs by his diſtinguiſhing between the Doctrines on his ſide, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Excluded Brethren, and thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he would make to be conſiſtent: which I ſhall diſprove, 1. By ſhewing what was the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Allegiance</hi> conſtantly received in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> not from the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, but from the beginning of the Reformation. And <hi>2ly,</hi> What is the different Doctrine that hath been taught by him and his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59635:6"/>Excluded Brethren, and the Reader may gueſs how irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable they are.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons of this my endeavour, are, 1. The great Scandal that might juſtly be imputed to the Church, if ſhe ſhould be ſo inconſtant as to recede from her own Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> From the jealouſie which the Kings, under whoſe protection the Church ſubſiſts, might entertain of her, if the Doctrine of <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> ſhould be allowed by her.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> Becauſe in the caſe which hath now hapned, ſhe hath not made uſe of any <hi>Reſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly,</hi> Becauſe ſome whom the Author calls Super-loyal and Super conforming perſons, for their maintaining the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> may be thought to have now caſt it off, and are diſpoſed to engage in a Rebellion againſt a lawful Prince for Male-Adminiſtrations.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew what was the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Allegiance</hi> profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the firſt Reformation. The judgment of the Biſhops in the days of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and <hi>Edward</hi> VI. who were our firſt Reformers, did ſet forth a Book called, <hi>The Inſtitution of a Chriſtian Man,</hi> whereof <hi>Cranmer, Ridley,</hi> and other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, were the Compilers. On the fifth Commandment they ſay, <hi>Subjects be bound not to withdraw their Fealty, Truth, Love, and Obedience towards their Prince, for any cauſe whatſoever; ne for any cauſe may they conſpire against his Perſon, ne do any thing towards the hurt thereof, nor of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</hi> And by this Command they be bound to obey all the Laws, Proclamations, Precepts, and Commandments made by their Prince, except they be contrary to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God. And on the ſixth Commandment, <hi>No Subjects may draw the Sword against the Prince, for any cauſe whatſoever it be; and though Princes, which be the Supream Heads of their Realms do otherwiſe than they ought, yet God hath aſſigned no Judges over them in this World.</hi> To theſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Authors of the <hi>Homelies,</hi> whereof Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> is ſaid to be the Pen-man: Of theſe, the Author ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 32:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59635:7"/>
               <hi>That they teach us to ſubmit to lawful Authority, and to know our bounden Duty to common Authority; but they teach no Loyalty beſides or contrary to Law.</hi> Her <hi>Homelies</hi> no-where that I know of, aſſert the Errours that I have here condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or condemn any of the Poſitions I have here aſſerted.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Homely</hi> the firſt againſt Rebellion, ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>That Kings and Princes, as well the evil as the good, do reign by God's Ordinance, and that Subjects are bound to obey them. If Servants ought to obey their Maſters, not only being gentle, but froward, much more ought Subjects to be obedient to their ſharp and rigorous Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rebellion is worſe than the worſt Government of the worſt Prince that hitherto hath been. What if a Prince be evil indeed, and undiſcreet, and it is evident to all mens eyes that he is ſo? I ask again, what if it be long of the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Subjects that he is ſo, ſhall the Subjects by their wickedneſs both provoke God to give them an evil and indiſcreet Prince for their puniſhment, and alſo rebel againſt him and againſt God? Hear what the Scripture ſays, <hi>God makes a wicked man to reign, for the puniſhment of a people.</hi> Let us deſerve to have a good Prince, or let us patiently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and obey ſuch as we deſerve; and whether the Prince be good or evil, let us pray for his continuance and increaſe in Goodneſs, if he be good; or for his amendment, if he be Evil. Our Liturgy, our Articles, our Conſtitutions, do all inculcate the ſame Duty: So have the prime Biſhops and Miniſters of the Church, eſpecially Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in the Reigns of King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, who condemned the Doctrine of Reſiſtance as a Popiſh Doctrine. Thus Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in a Sermon preached <hi>July</hi> 26. 1640. when that unnatural Rebellion began, on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. ſays, <hi>That no conjuncture of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances whatſoever, can make that to be done at any time, which in it ſelf is unlawful, and to take up Arms against a lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, offenſive or defenſive, may not be done at any time, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59635:7"/>any caſe, upon any pretence whatſoever.</hi> And on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. As for our Accuſers, if no more were to be inſtanced in then that one accurſed Poſition alone, wherein notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their agreement in other things, they both (<hi>i e.</hi> the Diſſenters and Papiſts) do conſent, <hi>viz.</hi> That lawful Soveraigns may be by their Subjects reſiſted, and Arms taken up againſt them for the Cauſe of Religion, it were enough to make good the Challenge againſt them bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which is ſo notorious a piece of ungodlineſs, as no man that either feareth God or the King as he ought, can ſpeak or think of, without deteſtation.</p>
            <p>And beyond theſe Doctrines I ſuppoſe no Super-Loyalty hath been taught, nor beneath theſe hath the Church of <hi>England</hi> at any time practiſed. How they behaved themſelves in the Rebellion againſt <hi>Charles</hi> I. doth appear by their conſtant adherence to him, and ſacrificing their Lives and Fortunes to his Service. Their Loyalty to <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, was not any way culpable, unleſs their Super-Loyalty was a crime. And to <hi>James</hi> the Second, had not the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Rebellion, to which the Sectaries gave aſſiſtance, been oppoſed by thoſe of the Church, he might have been more certainly forced out of the World, than he was out of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Hitherto then we find no reſiſtance in the Doctrine or Practice of the Church; and I hope, that until there be any cauſe given, our preſent Gracious Soveraigns, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will on any malicious ſuggeſtions, or groundleſs jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, entertain a contrary Opinion of the Church, or any of her true Members.</p>
            <p>The only thing therefore to be conſidered is, what hath been done as to reſiſtance in this late Revolution; how the chief Biſhops of the Church behaved themſelves under his Reign is freſh in memory; that in all lawful things they yielded ſubmiſſion and obedience, and in things unlawfully impoſed, they made no reſiſtance, but ſubmitted to even
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59635:8"/>illegal Impoſitions, Fines, and Impriſonments, until the King's deſerting of them; whereby he became as if he were naturally dead; the caſe of <hi>Allegiance</hi> was altered and utterly ceaſed. It is but vainly objected, that the late King was forced to deſert the Government, which in truth he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended to adminiſter as he ought; which intention was evidently declared, notwithſtanding his Coronation-Oath, by the whole ſeries of his Government, having wholly devoted himſelf to the Counſels of Popiſh Miniſters, for the Subverſion of the Eſtabliſhed Religion and Laws, and for the ſetling of Popery and Arbitrary Government, at the coſt of his Life; wherein being by a wonderful Providence diſappointed, he choſe to deſert the Government, I ſay he <hi>Choſe,</hi> having declared, <hi>He would do it, or die in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe a man doth drink to that exceſs that he looſeth his Reaſon, and in his Drunkenneſs is guilty of Murder, or ſets his own Houſe on fire, and leaves it in a flame that threatneth the conſuming of the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſuch a perſon is by the Law adjudged a wilful Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and muſt ſuffer accordingly. And doubtleſs, if men be intoxicated by deſtructive Opinions, tending to their own, as well as the deſtruction of others, and by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy in them, commit things contrary to the Rules of Religion, Law, and Reaſon, and draw on themſelves a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of flying for it; ſuch actions ſhall be accounted voluntary: for thus when God gives up wilful Sinners, after long continuance in their ſins, againſt all the methods of Grace which have been deſpiſed by them, to follow the hardneſs of their own Hearts, and ungodly Luſts, all the ſins, as well thoſe committed before, as after their judiciary hardneſs, ſhall be imputed to them as their voluntary acts: ſo is it in this caſe. And if the Fires kindled by a drunken man in his fury be quenched, and that man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming more ſober, ſhall deſire to return again, when the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59635:8"/>Neighbourhood have juſt cauſe to ſuſpect he will return again to his former Madneſs, I cannot ſee that they have any reaſon to admit of him, or to confide in him.</p>
            <p>And that the late King did voluntarily forſake his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that which the Author ſays, is a material proof, <hi>(viz)</hi> That the King declared to a Perſon of Credit, <hi>That the Queen obtained from him a ſolemn Oath on the Sacrament, on the</hi> Sunday, <hi>That if ſhe went for</hi> France <hi>on</hi> Monday, <hi>he would not fail to follow her on</hi> Tueſday. And though his Subjects uſed ſome force to hinder his Flight, yet they uſed none to compel him to it.</p>
            <p>I may ſeem to call in queſtion the Judgment of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, if I ſhould think their Wiſe Counſel and Determination ſtood in need of any farther confirmation. I return therefore to ſhew what I chiefly intended, <hi>viz.</hi> that notwithſtanding any thing that hath been done by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> there is no cauſe to charge her with prevaricating in the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance:</hi> But the contrary is inſinuated in the Author, and other late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; as where, in <hi>p.</hi> 13. he ſays, <hi>In ſome caſes a Defenſive Reſiſtance may not not only be lawful, but a neceſſary Duty.</hi> P. 14. <hi>Whatever Grievance is without or contrary to Law, the Subject is not bound to bear it, and we are not bound to yield Paſſive Obedience to the King. That in ſome unhappy Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> (which he mentioneth) <hi>the Subjects will be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable before God, if they uſe ſo much Reſiſtance as he hath made neceſſary for preſerving the Government and themſelves.</hi> Pag. 18. He mentioneth the depoſing of <hi>Edward</hi> II. and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> II. to prove, that the Nobles and Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may remove a King from his Government. Pag. 26. <hi>When the Kingdoms of the World are become Chriſt's by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating his Religion among their Civil Rights, then we may uſe any Expedients for the Defence of our Religion, which we may uſe in defending any Priviledges of our Civil Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>If it was lawful for the People of</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59635:9"/>England, <hi>in an extream neceſſity, to remove a King whoſe Government was become inconſiſtent with the Publick Weal, and to ſet up another, by whom the Publick Intereſt may be ſecured, it is lawful ſtill, notwithſtanding our Oaths or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Theſe Poſitions are ſo far from any conſiſtency with the Church-<hi>Homelies,</hi> that they were the grounds on which the War againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt was carried on, and on which the prevailing People and Souldiery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him, and might have ſet up <hi>Cromwel</hi> to be their King. Pag. 33, 34. Having mentioned divers inſtances for Reſiſtance, he concludes, <hi>Such were the Principles of the Church of</hi> England <hi>in the Reign of Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>and King</hi> James. And <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>That the Principles of Loyalty were no other at that time, than what he had aſſerted, we may eaſily ſatisfie our ſelves from that Form of Prayer they are charged with by the Parliament in Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s Reign,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That God would turn her heart from Idolatry, to the true Faith, or elſe ſhorten her days, and take her quickly out of the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now certainly this Form of Prayer was not in the Church-Liturgy, but it is as certain that they were the Foamings of ſome Extemporary Zealots in their Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; concerning which, the Act 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſays, Such a Prayer was never heard or read of to be uſed by any good Chriſtian man againſt any Prince, though he were a Pagan.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> had learnt to pray for them that perſecute them, to bleſs, and not to curſe their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, eſpecially Kings, and thoſe that were in Authority: I ſhall therefore commend the Author to Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> for his information what ſort of People uſed this Form of Prayer, <hi>p.</hi> 65. of his Second Part of <hi>The Loyalty of Pious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> where he ſays, <hi>That Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s zealous Proteſtant Biſhops, Miniſters, and Subjects likewiſe, made conſtant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for her; but ſome over zealous Anabaptiſtical Fanaticks, uſing ſome unchriſtian Prayers againſt her, That God would cut
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59635:9"/>her off and ſhorten her days, occaſioned this ſpecial Act againſt ſuch Prayers.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 66. he adds, <hi>Theſe Prayers were much againſt, and directly contrary to the Judgment of Archbiſhop</hi> Cranmer, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Farrer, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hooper, Rowland Taylor, John Philpot, John Bradford, Edward Crome, John Rogers, Laurence Sanders, Edward Laurence, Miles Coverdale, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Exon, <hi>and others of our godly Proteſtant Biſhops and Miniſters, who ſoon after ſuffered as Martyrs.</hi> (And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the rather for this Provocation:) for in their Letter, <hi>May</hi> 8. 1554. they profeſs, <hi>That as obedient Subjects, we ſhall behave our ſelves towards Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>and all that be in Authority, and not ceaſe to pray to God for them, that he would govern them all generally and particularly with the Spirit of Widſom and Grace; and ſo we heartily pray and deſire all men to do, in no point conſenting to any kind of Rebellion or Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt our Soveraign Lady; but where they cannot obey, but muſt diſobey God, there to ſubmit themſelves with all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and humility, to ſuffer what the will and pleaſure of the Higher Powers ſhall adjudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> wrote his Apology againſt the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Reports made of him, that he ſhould encourage and maintain ſuch as curſed Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> wherein he vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates his Innocency and Loyalty, in praying for Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now how ingenuouſly theſe things are objected to the firſt Reformers of the Church to caſt a Scandal on them, I leave to the impartial Reader to judge; as alſo whether the Doctrines and Practices of ſuch as diſſented from her, which are neither ſeaſonable nor grateful to be now recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can give our Governours better ſecurity for their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, than that which the Author calls Super-Loyalty. And I am confident it cannot be ſuſpected, that that Church which oppoſed that Floud of Arbitrary Power which was breaking in upon them, refuſing the publiſhing of that Declaration, which would have owned the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59635:10"/>Power, to their great hazard, and did ſo innocently and patiently <hi>wait for the ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> will caſt off their Super-Loyalty to our preſent moſt gracious King and Queen, whom God and the Nation have ſo wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed. For my part, I think that although on the preſent occaſion and emergencies, we do part with ſome extraordinary ſupplies, we ſhall make a very advantageous Bargain and cheap Purchaſe of the Re-eſtabliſhment of our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, which were ſo nigh to a total Subverſion: And for the preſervation whereof, if it had been lawful, we ſhould not have counted our Bloud too dear.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59635:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
